Guide to the Detroit Statler Hotel collection, 1823-2014.
Detroit Statler Hotel collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Detroit Statler Hotel collection, 1823-2014.
8471
Kukan, Scott,
.4 cubic feet.
Reports, printed materials, photographs, publications and architectural plans.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Reports, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, floor plans, and ephemera relating to the hotel and the history of the site where it was built.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
The Detroit Statler Hotel, also known as the Statler-Hilton and Detroit Heritage Hotel, was designed by George B. Post and Louis Rorimer. Consisting of 18 stories and containing 800 rooms, it was built in 1915 at 1539 Washington Boulevard in Detroit, Michigan. Although popular at one time, it fell into disuse by 1975 and was demolished in 2005.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Reports, magazine articles, newspaper clippings, photographs, floor plans, and ephemera relating to the hotel and the history of the site where it was built.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Kukan, Scott,; Statler Hotel (Detroit, Mich.)
Subjects:
Hotels -- Michigan -- Detroit.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Ellsworth M. Statler and Statler Hotels Company
  - Biographies, 1863-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - E.M. Statler, "Hotel Man of the Half Century" (Master's Thesis), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Overview of The Hotel Statler-Detroit, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    D. Kohrman
- Series II. Statler comes to Detroit, 1907-1915, 1907-1915
  - "Arthur H. Fleming Pays Quarter of Million for the Bagley Homestead" from The Detroit Journal, 1907-10-02 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History of the Statler Hotel Site, 1823-1907 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Hotel Statler-Detroit" from The Detroiter, 3(12), 1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Hotel Statler Now Close to Completion" from Michigan Manufacturer and Financial Record, 14(9), 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Construction photograph, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Floor Plan at Hotel Statler" and "First Guests of the Hotel Statler" from The Detroit News, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "New Statler is Monument to the Boards Activities" The Detroiter, 6(20), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Hotel Statler, Detroit, Mich." from Architecture and Building, 67(3), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Postcards, photographs, postage stamps, and building advertisements, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series III. E.M. Statler era, 1915-1928, 1915-1928
  - Hotel letterhead, Hotels Statler Virginia Rounds Cigarette package, Plese "Do Not Disturb" door sign, Business card for Paul T. Kilborn (Credit Manager), Statler Service Codes manual, Park Avenue advertisement showing Statler in view, Hotels Statler Company Inc. Bonds, Hotel advertisements, 1915-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings/photo of proposed, new Statler Hotel, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1919-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of exterior and kitchen, 1915-1928 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings from The Yearbook of the Architectural League, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Hotel Butcher Garde Manger and Carver, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Statler Idea in Hotel Planning and Equipment" from The Architectural Forum, 37(5), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "Ability Wins Out" from The Gas Industry, 16(7), 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Largest Hotel in the World: And some reasons for E.M. Statler's spectacular success" from The Independent 103, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hotel Statler, Detroit - Floor Plans, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Hotel Statler in Detroit" from The Architectural Record, Undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - "The Hotel Pennsylvania" from The Architectural Review, 8(3), 1919 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series IV. The post E.M. Statler era, 1929-1958, 1929-1958
  - Exterior Photographs, 1929-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Exterior Photograph, Undated (Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera: Envelopes, Guest Account Statements, Star the Statler Cities brochure, Statler Special Services brochure, Statler Service Codes manual, You and Your Hotel employee manual, Statler Hotel ink blotter, 1954 Credit Card, Menus and wine lists, Room Rates, Luggage tags, Magazine advertisements, Company letterhead, Hotel Statler "Air Mail" label, Announcement of the Terrace Dining Room, Convention planning guide, 1929-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1937-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hotel Statler Guest magazine, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hotel Statler News magazine, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Hotel Pennsylvania Ephemera: Envelopes, Guest account statement, Advertising brochure, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hotel renovation from The Architectural Record 83(1), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Convention booklet, Undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Old Guard Association Banquet photographs, 1951-1952, 1955-1956 (Folder 1)
- Series V. The decline, 1959-1975, 1959-1975
  - Miscellaneous Ephemera: Interior restaurant photographs, Room Service menu, Hilton: Detroit advertisement booklet, Sending blank, 1959-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Hilton Welcomes Statler Hotels to Family" from Life Magazine, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Series VI. Abandonment, 1975-1999, 1975-1999
  - Newspaper clippings, 1975-1999 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series VII. Revitalization and demolition, 1999-2004, 1999-2004
  - Correspondence to save Statler Hotel, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - EPA and DEQ documentation on hazerdous materials disposal, Undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Specification and Project Manual for Demolition, Removal and Disposal of Former Statler Hilton Hotel, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)